Dileep Kumar Latchireddi

+1 (571)-279-9321 | dileep1228.gmu@gmail.com | linkedin.com/in/dileepkumar1228/ | Portfolio

SUMMARY:

Computer Science graduate student with 3+ years of experience in backend development. Strong Object-oriented programming skills and well versed in Data structures and Algorithms. Experienced in cloud technologies, known for building and delivering highquality, scalable and modular **RESTful** micro services to enhance user experiences.

SKILLS:

Languages: C++, C, Java, Python, SQL, JavaScript, TypeScript, HTML5, CSS.

Web Development: Node.js, React.js, Next.js, Express.js, Tailwind.

Databases: MySQL, MongoDB, PostgreSQL, Redis, NoSQL.

Infrastructure and Cloud Services: AWS, Google Cloud Services, Docker, Kubernetes, Elastic Search.

Algorithm & Design: Algorithms, Design Patterns, Object-Oriented Design, Microservices.

Testing, Monitoring & Logging: JUnit testing, Mockito, Postman, Grafana.

Version Control & Collaboration: Git, Jira, Scrum, Agile methodologies, Jenkins, CI/CD.

Other: Figma, gRPC, Apache Kafka, JSON, XML, REST, SOAP, MVC, Maven, Spring MVC, JPA, Hibernate.

WORK EXPERIENCE:

George Mason University, Fairfax, USA.

Graduate Teaching Assistant

January 2023 - May 2024

- As a GTA for Introduction to Problem Solving using Java with 60+ students, delivered constructive feedback, conducted grading, and pinpointed areas of enhancement, resulting in improved class performance.
- Developed and delivered lab exercises, 1 on 1 sessions and recorded the solutions for the students to help students learn and grow. Virtusa, India **Software Development Engineer - 1 September 2020 - June 2022**
- Spearheaded the integration of cutting-edge fraud and risk detection algorithms for transactional operations, collaborating with a cross-functional team of six. Bolstered transactional security and risk management, improving fraud detection by nearly 15%.
- Optimized database performance by introducing PostgreSQL read replicas and database indexes, resulting in a 90% reduction in query response time and enhanced system performance.
- Performed in-depth codebase analysis for up to 18 modules and re-implemented encryption and decryption procedures on sensitive data like SSN, banking accounts, and mobile numbers.
- Optimized critical components of the fraud detection API/Database, resulting in a substantial reduction of response time by 5ms. Tech Stack: Java, Spring Boot, Apache Subversion, Postgres, Kubernetes, AWS.

OYO Rooms, Hyderabad, India

Software Development Engineer – 1.

June 2019 - September 2020

- Created Hotel Audit / Cost calculation logic which involved maintaining 1000s of rules related to hotel items and pricing logic across multiple geographies, resulting in the automation of 60-80% of manual work.
- Led the development of the instant wallet refund feature with Java, ensuring thread safety and managing concurrent data access, reducing processing time from 7-14 days to 1 hour.
- Collaborated on a new lead-to-live process, streamlining hotel onboarding across multiple geographies, reducing on-boarding time from 2-3 weeks to 2-3 days.

Tech Stack: JavaScript, Express, React, Postgres, Redis, MongoDB, Postman, Kubernetes, AWS.

PROJECTS:

Blogging App | React, Express.js, TypeScript, Prisma, Cloudflare, ZOD, Versel.

Built a blogging app using React, TypeScript, Prisma ORM, PostgreSQL, JWT authentication, and Cloudflare deployment. Incorporated features such as data validation, authentication, session management, connection pooling.

StyleGAN | Python, Pytorch, Deep Learning, GANs

Implemented a Style based Generative Adversarial Network which is capable not only of generating impressively photorealistic high-quality photos of faces but also offers control over the style of the generated image at different levels of detail through varying the style vectors and noise.

Student Survey | React, Spring Boot, DevOps, Docker, Kubernetes, Jenkins, CI/CD, AWS.

- Built a Student Survey single-page application and integrated it into EC2 instance, and managed data by RDS services.
- Established a robust CI/CD pipeline with GitHub and Jenkins, automating the Setup, testing, and deployment processes for streamlined development workflows that helped thereby reducing the running time by 10%.

EDUCATION

George Mason University

Master of Science in Computer Science. GPA - 3.89/4

ANITS College Bachelor of Technology in Computer Science. GPA: 8.6/10 Fairfax, VA, USA

August 2022 - May 2024 Visakhapatnam, AP, India

August 2015 - May 2019